A Guide to the Gary Ann Giovanni Culinary Papers, 1997-2004
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Gary Ann Giovanni Culinary Papers, 1997-2004
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Giovanni, Gary Ann, 1940-2005
Ms2006-011
3.5 Cubic Feet 3 boxes
Papers of Gary Ann Giovanni, a chef, caterer and cooking teacher active in Blacksburg, Virginia. The collection contains records, menus, and recipes from her catering jobs and from the cooking classes she taught for the local YMCA Open University. Also includes material related to the various community organizations for which Gary worked or volunteered, and some material associated with her sister, poet Nikki Giovanni.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Gary Ann Giovanni Culinary Papers were donated to the Special Collections in 2005.
Biographical Information
Gary Ann Giovanni was born in September 1940 in Knoxville, Tennessee and attended Central State University in Ohio. She married young, divorced, and then married Joe Black, the first African American to pitch in a World Series and had one son with him. In 1973, Giovanni graduated from Xavier University in Cincinnati, Ohio. Giovanni volunteered with Fannie Lou Hamer in delivering Christmas turkeys in Mississippi during the Civil Rights movement. She attended the California Culinary Academy, studying with master pastry chef Bo Freiburg, as well as with pastry chef Jim Dodge at the Stanford Court Hotel, chef Herbert Keller of Fleur de Lys, and many others. For five years, Giovanni owned and ran a full-service catering business in Oakland, California. Giovanni worked for SeaLand Corporation in Oakland, California until 1994 when she retired and moved with her mother to Blacksburg, Virginia, where her sister, poet Nikki Giovanni, lives. While in Blacksburg, Giovanni opened a catering business with Rebecca Isenhour which they named B.I.G.G., the acronym representing both of their initials. At the same time, Giovanni taught numerous well-received classes through the YMCA's Open University program. She studied at several of the Greenbrier's cooking workshops. In 2005, Giovanni was diagnosed with a brain tumor. She died that August in Blacksburg, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The majority of this collection contains detailed information about the various catering jobs and "Open U" YMCA classes that Gary Ann Giovanni handled during her ten years in Blacksburg, Virginia. There is some material related to her sister Nikki Giovanni, most related to various speaking activities or awards. Other items of interest include printed menus and recipes from Giovanni's attendance at the Greenbrier's cooking school, as well as food-related ephemera (pamphlets and other media produced by various food companies or publishers).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series, one of which has two subseries. Most series are ordered by subject, but the catering jobs and classes are arranged chronologically.
Series I: Family. This series contains personal information about Gary Ann Giovanni and her family. It is arranged by person.
Series II: Community Involvement. This series highlights Giovanni's community involvement in non-culinary activities. Church, sorority, and other activities are represented.
Series III: Professional Activity-Culinary. General information about professional acticity is followed by two sub-series with records of: A. Catering and B. Teaching at the Open U, each of which are arranged by date.
Series IV: Professional Activity-Non-Culinary. This small series is organized by subject.
Series V: Miscellaneous. This series contains Black culture ephemera arranged by subject.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); History of Food and Drink; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.)
Contents List
- Family
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains personal information about Gary Ann Giovanni and her family. The material about her sister, poet Nikki Giovanni, contains information about her activities and awards that she received.
  - Gary Ann Giovanni
    - Writings, personal letters, articles (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 2002 desk calendar containing photos of Gary Giovanni (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Litigation (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Joe Black (husband) and Christopher A. Black (son) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Nikki Giovanni (sister) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Thomas Giovanni (nephew) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Yolande Cornelia Giovanni (mother) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Other family (aunts) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Community Involvement
  This series highlights Giovanni's community involvement in non-culinary activities. Material pertaining to St. Paul's African Methodist Episcopal Church, the Delta Sigma Theta Sorority, Inc./Blacksburg Alumnae Chapter, and miscellaneous references to Giovanni's Oakland ties (chiefly with activist Mitch Snyder) make up the bulk of this series. In addition, the material about the AME and the Delta Sigma Sorority contains information of interest to those researching these institutions and their role during the time Giovanni belonged to them. Conferences and projects that Giovanni was associated with are well represented.
  - St. Paul African Methodist Episcopal Church, Blacksburg, Virginia (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority, Inc. Blacksburg Alumnae Chapter (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous organizational memberships (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Professional Activity, Culinary
  The two chronologically arranged subseries, A. Catering Jobs and B. YMCA Open University Classes, form the bulk of this series. Each catering job file is listed by client name and date, and contains menus, recipes, information about clients, grocery lists, and receipts with food prices. Most of Giovanni's catering jobs were for faculty and administration at Virginia Tech. YMCA cooking class files contain student-attendee lists, menus, recipes, and sometimes general information about the cuisine if the class focused on an aspect of international cooking. The series also contains some handwritten recipes and food-related ephemera, the latter of interest to those researching food media and publications/pamphlets. Greenbrier menus and recipes enhance the series.
  - Miscellaneous recipes, personal and handwritten (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Greenbrier, recipes and classes attended (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Greenbrier, three menus, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Catering Jobs
    - Miscellaneous Menus for Stacy, New Orleans and African (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Catering Business Sample Menus (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - University Club Tea, Menu Planning Set, 05/01/1998 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - General Catering Information Used in Setting Up B.I.G.G. Catering Company (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Competitors of B.I.G.G. Catering Company (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Arnold, 05/03/? (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Snyder, Cooper House, Presbyterian Campus Ministry, Virginia Tech, 01/14/1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Town of Blacksburg, International Student Fruit and Dessert Social, 08/20/1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Norstedt, 09/26/1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Giovanni, Jazz Breakfast, 09/28/1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Pendergrass, Dean of Students, Virginia Tech, 10/27/1998, 11/12/1998 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - "Y" Festival (YMCA), 11/13-11/15/1998 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - St. Paul's AME Church, 11/08/1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Green, 11/13/1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Town of Blacksburg, Reception for New City Manager, 11/19/1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Plaut, Faculty Development Committee, "Teaching the Feminists to Float", 12/10/1998 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Lesko, 01/04-01/05/1999 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Green, 01/20/1999 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Ellett, 02/28/1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Giovanni, 3/23/1999, 4/13/1999, 4/20/1999 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Pendergrass, Dean of Students, Virginia Tech, 03/27/1999 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Harshberger, Tea, 03/27/1999 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Delta Sigma Theta, Inc., Dance (cancelled), 04/24/1999 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Plaut, Faculty Development Committee, 04/24/1999 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Norstedt, 04/30/1999 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Pendergrass, Dean of Students, Virginia Tech, 04/30/1999 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Boule, Luncheon, Hubbell Lighting, 05/03/1999 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Collins, Virginia Tech Women's Studies, 05/10/1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - University Club Brunch, 05/27/1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - St. Paul's AME Church, Regional Meeting Lunch, 06/19/1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Hershberger, 07/07/1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Burke, Hubbell Lighting Corporate Lunch, 08/10/1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Distler, Virginia Tech School of the Arts, 08/16/1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Mezzaros, Virginia Tech Provost, 09/15/1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Dunay, Virginia Tech Foundation, 09/18/1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Missionary Area Meeting, A.M.E., 10/23/1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Women's Studies, Virginia Tech, 09/25/1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Distler, Virginia Tech School of the Arts, 09/30/1999, 10/01/1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Norstedt, 10/01/1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Britt, 10/03/1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Delta Sigma Theta, Inc., Cluster Meeting, 10/09/1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Floyd-Thomas, 10/19/1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Women's Studies, Virginia Tech, 10/29/1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Dunay, Virginia Tech Foundation, 11/13/1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Switzer, 11/25/1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Women's Studies, Virginia Tech, 12/09/1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Floyd-Thomas, 12/10/1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Downey, 12/11/1999 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Clemenz, 12/17/1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Holt, 01/02/2000 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Pendergrass, Dean of Students, Virginia Tech, 01/31/2000 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Gordon, Reception at Virginia Tech, 02/16/2000 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Switzer (cancelled), 2/26/2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Women's Studies, Virginia Tech, 02/24/2000, 02/18/2000, 02/25/2000, 03/02/2000, 04/14/2000 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Pendergrass, Dean of Students, Virginia Tech, 02/23/2000 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Merola, Dean, Virginia Tech, 03/09/2000 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Beverly, 03/24/2000 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Pendergrass, Dean of Students, Virginia Tech, 05/04/2000 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Planned Parenthood (cancelled), 05/05/2000 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Carlisle, 05/07/2000 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Gordon, Reception at Virginia Tech, 05/10/2000 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Women's Center Retreat, Virginia Tech, 05/10/2000 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Pendergrass, Dean of Students, Virginia Tech (cancelled), 05/12/2000 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Christiansburg Institute, Reception, 05/19/2000 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Rutherford, 05/21/2000 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Flick, 05/27/2000 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Day, 06/03/2000 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Kark, 06/26/2000 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Switzer, 07/03/2000 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Vernon, Faculty Senate President, Virginia Tech, 08/29/2000 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Norstedt, 09/22/2000 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Gilmore, Women's Studies, Virginia Tech, 09/28/2000 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Floyd-Thomas, 10/15/2000 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Stephenson, 11/14/2000 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Fine, Interdisciplinary Studies, Virginia Tech, Reception at Cranwell Center, 01/17/2001 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Norstedt, 02/24/2001 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Floyd-Thomas, 02/25/2001 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Floyd-Thomas, Women's Studies Retreat, 03/15/2001 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Stubbs (cancelled), 03/19/2001 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Office of Multicultural Affairs, "A Place at the Table," with Nikki Giovanni, John Egerton, and Edna Lewis, 04/04/2001 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Floyd-Thomas, Birthday party, 04/05/2001 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Eaves, Stepping Conference, Virginia Tech, 04/06/2001 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Brown, Wine Award Reception, Virginia Tech, 04/22/2001 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Hyer, 04/27/2001 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Vernon, Faculty Senate President, Virginia Tech, 04/29/2001 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Creamer, 08/02/2001 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Holtzman (cancelled), 08/05/2001 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Norstedt, 09/15/2001 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Montgomery County Social Services, 12/12/2001 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Hyer, 12/12/2001 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Creamer, 02/20/2002 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Vernon, Faculty Senate President, Virginia Tech, 08/17/2002 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Watterson, 09/07/2002 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Giovanni (Gary's dog), 09/15/2002 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Kark, 11/08/2002 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Watterson, 11/27/2002 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Resiger, 12/12/2002 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Kark (gift), 01/11/2003 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Myers, 02/07/2003 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Vernon, Faculty Senate President, Virginia, 02/08/2003 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Blacksburg High School, 03/05/2003 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Giovanni, Juke Joint Class, 03/18/2003 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority, Inc., 04/26/2003 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Eaves, 04/28/2003 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Hyer, 05/09/2003 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - McCann, 09/19/2003 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Warden, 09/30/2003 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Weber, Wedding rehersal, 10/04/2003 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Eaves, Social Services, 11/13/2003 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - YMCA Crafts Fair Committee Lunch, 12/01/2003 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Harrison, School of the Arts, Virginia Tech, 12/11/2003 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Rock, 12/202/2003 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Women's Studies, Virginia Tech (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Delta Sigma Theta Sorority, Inc., 03/19/2004 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Philpot, Office of Student Life, Virginia Tech, 03/27/2004 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Kilkilly, 05/06/2004 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - McCann, 09/12/2004 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Giovanni, Party, 10/19/2004 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - YMCA Open University Classes
    - Hors d'Oeuvres, 02/12/1997 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Tarts: From Sweet to Savory, 04/01/1998 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Chinese Cooking, 04/22/1998 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Tapas, 09/24/1998 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Thai Cooking, 09/10/1998 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Foods of India, 10/14/1998 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Veggie Magic, 11/02/1998 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - An Edible Christmas, 11/18/1998 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Southwestern/New Mexican Christmas, 12/02/1998 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Low-Fat, Low Cholesterol, 02/03/1999 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Soups, 02/11/1999 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Casseroles, 02/25/1999 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Easter Brunch, 03/31/1999 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Thai Cooking II, 04/25/1999 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Bread in the Food Processor, 04/18/1999 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Summer Fare, 04/28/1999 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Chicken for All Seasons, 09/23/1999 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Breakfast, 09/28/1999 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Almost Vegetarian Entertaining, 10/07/1999 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Fat-Free Holiday Recipes, 11/15/1999 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Holiday Buffet, 12/02/1999 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - A Fat-Free Lovers Feast, 02/02/2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Pasta and Pizza, 02/22/2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mediterranean Cooking, 03/29/2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Outdoor Entertaining, 04/25/2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - French Cooking, 09/26/2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Halloween Party, 10/24/2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Holiday Buffet, 11/29/2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - More Mexican, 02/27/2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Soups, 02/01/2001 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Chinese Cooking, 09/29/2001 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Breakfast Any Time of the Day, 11/13/2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Holiday Hors d'Oeuvres, 12/06/2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Dinner Party Menus, 04/02/2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Dinner at the Greenbrier, 02/04/2002 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - New Orleans Mardi Gras Party, 2/21/2002, 2/28/2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Greek Fare, 04/04/2002 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Spring Dinner at the Greenbrier, 04/09/2002 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Retro Cooking, 04/15/2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Wine and Hors d'Oeuvres, 11/12/2002, 11/19/2002 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Christmas Hors d'Oeuvres, 12/05/2002 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Thai Cooking, 02/13/2003 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Mother/Daughter Cooking, 03/03/2003 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - C. Warden Cooking Class (private), 03/27/2003 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Wine and Food Pairings, 04/01/2003, 04/08/2003 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Mexican Cooking, 04/16/2003 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Greenbrier Entertaining, 04/24/2003 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Thai Cooking, 04/30/2003, 05/01/2003 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Indonesian Rijsttafel, 09/11/2003 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - What's for Supper?, 09/17/2003 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Wine and Cheese, 09/23/2003, 09/30/2003 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Korean Cooking, 10/08/2003 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Tips and Techniques, 11/12/2003 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Egyptian Cooking, 11/13/2003 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Canapes and Appetizers, 12/02/2003 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - A Casual Buffet, 02/12/2004 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Food from the Polynesian Islands, 02/26/2004 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Pleasures of the Vietnamese Table, 03/16/2004 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Fresh Flavors, 04/13/2004 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Back Yard Bash, 04/27/2004 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Tuscan Sunday Dinner, 05/06/2004 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Grilling 101, 06/16/2004 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Southern-Style Cooking, 07/14/2004 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Souffles, 09/14/2004 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Grilling 101, Part II, 09/21/2004 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - French Cooking, 10/05/2004 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Mexican Cooking, 10/16/2004 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Puff Pastry - The Miracle Dough, 11/28/2004 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Christmas Hors d'Oeuvres (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Professional Activity, Non-Culinary
  - YMCA: YMCA Minutes and Staff Meeting Notes/Gary Giovanni employment letters, crafts fair income statement (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - YMCA: General Guide to the YMCA at Virginia Tech (staff handbook) (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous employment, law school admission correspondence (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Miscellaneous Materials and Documents
  - Black culture (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Food and Cooking-Related Ephemera
    - Menus from restaurants (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - McCall's Cooking School illustrated recipes (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Creative Cook's Kitchen and Great American Recipes, illustrated recipes (Box 3, Folder 55)